Finding Aid for Washtenaw Abstract Company records ca. 1824-1954
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Washtenaw Abstract Company records circa 1824-1954
Washtenaw Abstract Company (Ann Arbor, Mich.)
19 oversize folders
1 linear feet
42 volumes
Land title company based in Ann Arbor, Michigan. Abstracts of mortgages, deeds, and other legal papers recorded in Washtenaw County; and plat maps for Washtenaw County additions and subdivisions.
8544 Bb.2 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was donated by the estate of Helen Brown Haller (donor 6321 ), the daughter of Arthur Brown, in 1979, and by Transnation Title Insurance Co. (donor 8782 ), in 1998.
The collection is open for research.
Arthur Brown, who was at that time the county clerk of Washtenaw County, founded the Washtenaw Abstract Company in 1893. The company succeeded the abstracting business of C.H. Manly, which had been founded about 1881 with offices in the county courthouse.
The Washtenaw Abstract Company's offices were initially located in the county courthouse, but were moved in 1895, when Brown's term as clerk ended, to the Lawrence Block in Ann Arbor, where Brown's law office was also located. In 1911, the company's office was moved to 106 North Fourth Avenue, Ann Arbor, where it remained until the company was taken over by Lawyers Title Insurance Corporation in 1961. In 1998 Lawyers Title was in turn taken over by Transnation Title Insurance Company.
The collection contains two series of abstracts of Washtenaw County land ownership and transaction records and two series of plat maps.
Subjects:
Ann Arbor (Mich.)--History.; Real property--Michigan--Washtenaw County.; Land use--Michigan--Washtenaw County.; Washtenaw County (Mich.)--Maps.; Real property--Michigan--Washtenaw County--Maps.; Peoples Abstract Company.
- Abstracts of mortgages 1825-1954
  The Abstract of Mortgages series (volumes numbered for storage vol. 24-42) contains abstracts of mortgages from 1825 through 1954. This series covers Ann Arbor, Ypsilanti, the villages in the county, and the townships, with the exception of Salem and Superior Townships. These volumes seem to have been first compiled in the early 1880s. They were kept up-to-date with later mortgages until 1954.
  - Ann Arbor
    - "Abstract Book 1" (Volume 24)
    - "Ann Arbor Mortgages 2" (Volume 25)
    - "Abstracts 3" (Volume 26)
    - "Ann Arbor Mortgage Record 4" (Volume 27)
    - "Mortgages 5" (Volume 28)
  - Ypsilanti
    - "Mortgages Ypsilanti City" (Volume 29)
    - "Ypsilanti Mortgages" (Volume 30)
    - "Ypsilanti Mortgages 3" (Volume 31)
  - Villages
    - "Mortgages Ann Arbor City, Villages" (Volume 32)
    - "Village Mortgages No. 2" (Volume 33)
  - Townships
    - Dexter/Lima (Volume 34)
    - Freedom/Bridgewater (Volume 35)
    - Lodi/Saline (Volume 36)
    - Lyndon/Sylvan (Volume 37)
    - Northfield/Ann Arbor (Volume 38)
    - Pittsfield/York (Volume 39)
    - Scio/Webster (Volume 40)
    - Sharon/Manchester (Volume 41)
    - Ypsilanti/Augusta (Volume 42)
- Miscellaneous volumes, chiefly 1825-1882
  The second abstract series, titled Miscellaneous Volumes, (volumes numbered for storage vol. 1-23) includes abstracts of deeds, mortgages, and other legal papers from the earliest years of the county's existence to about 1882. The last items in the series were created around 1912, about the time the company moved its offices. This series is made up of three groups of material:
  Volumes 1-8 include miscellaneous abstracts, on a countywide basis, and do not seem well organized.
  Volumes 9-15 include abstracts of mortgages for the period 1829-1882, for each city, village, and township in Washtenaw County.
  Volumes 16-23 include separate lists of abstracts of deeds and of mortgages for the period ca. 1825 to 1882, for cities, villages, and townships. The collection is not complete, with Ann Arbor city and township missing, along with several other townships and villages.
  - Index to early deeds[?] and mortgages of Ann Arbor and deeds[?] of Ypsilanti, arranged by addition undated (Volume 1)
  - Index to deeds for lands sold for unpaid taxes, arranged by township 1831-1834 (Volume 2)
  - Abstracts of mortgages recorded
    - Arranged by township 1825-1851 (Volume 3)
    - Arranged roughly chronologically 1873-1874 (Volume 4)
      (with a few earlier items 1867-1872 and a few property histories)
  - Abstracts of deeds recorded, arranged roughly chronologically
    - 1873-1876 (Volume 5)
      (with a few property histories and earlier items, 1836-1872)
    - circa 1824-1869 (Volume 6)
      (includes some wills, powers of attorney, and liens)
  - Abstracts of wills recorded 1840s-circa 1912 (Volume 7)
    (arranged alphabetically, letter A missing)
    (also includes powers of attorney and other documents; for earlier years this is an index only)
  - Tract book of village plats, with property histories for some lots undated (Volume 8)
  - Abstracts of mortgages recorded 1829-1882
    - Ann Arbor City, arranged by addition (Volume 9)
    - Ypsilanti City and Saline, Manchester, Milan, Mooreville, and Rawsonville Villages, arranged by addition (Volume 10)
    - Lyndon, Sylvan, Sharon, and Manchester Townships (Volume 11)
    - Dexter, Lima, Freedom, and Bridgewater Townships (Volume 12)
    - Webster, Scio, Lodi, and Saline Townships (Volume 13)
    - Northfield, Pittsfield, Ann Arbor, and York Townships (Volume 14)
    - Salem, Superior, Ypsilanti, and Augusta Townships (Volume 15)
  - Abstracts of deeds and mortgages recorded circa 1825-1882
    - Dexter Village and Lima and Scio Townships (Volume 16)
    - Dexter and Webster Townships (Volume 17)
    - Freedom and Bridgewater Townships (Volume 18)
    - Manchester Village and Sharon and Manchester Townships (Volume 19)
    - Saline Village and Saline and York Townships (Volume 20)
    - Saline No. 2 (Volume 21)
      (includes Saline and Mooreville Villages and Saline Township)
    - Superior and Augusta Townships (Volume 22)
    - Ypsilanti City and Township (Volume 23)
- Plat maps
  The first plat map series contains primarily photostats of plats taken from the county record books. Most of these are arranged by name of plat, with Assessors Plats in a separate sequence and separate, smaller, groupings for "Alphabet deed maps" and "Deed maps and Liber maps." For the most part, these are strictly plats, and do not show land ownership.
  The second plat map series overlaps the first series to some extent. These maps were originally bound in a large volume titled "Peoples Abstract Co. Map Book of Washtenaw County" which was taken apart for preservation purposes. As with the first plat map series, these are strictly plats, and do not generally show land ownership.
  - Plat Maps circa 1825-1957 (Outsize unbound material)
    - Alphabet deed maps (Box 1)
    - Assessor's plats (Box 1)
    - Plats A-Z, 13 folders (Box 1)
    - Deed maps and Liber maps (Box 1)
  - Plat maps circa 1825-1912
    (includes hand-drawn and blueprint maps of city and village plats and additions)
    (Outsize storage in basement)
    - Ann Arbor
      (also includes plats in Ann Arbor and Pittsfield Townships later annexed to Ann Arbor)
      - Named plats
        - A-B (Folder 1)
        - C-E (Folder 2)
        - F-L (Folder 3)
        - M-R (Folder 4)
        - S-T (Folder 5)
        - U-Z (Folder 6)
      - Miscellaneous
        (a few of these maps show property ownership)
        - East of Main Street (Folder 7)
        - West of Main Street and plats showing both east and west sides (Folder 8)
    - Chelsea (Folder 9)
    - Dexter (Folder 10)
    - Manchester (Folder 11)
    - Milan (Folder 12)
    - Saline (Folder 13)
    - Ypsilanti
      - Named plats A-Loriginal plat, and miscellaneous (Folder 14)
      - Named plats M-Z (Folder 15)
    - Miscellaneous plats, arranged by township
      - Townships 1 South (Lyndon, Dexter, Webster, Northfield, and Salem Townships) (Folder 16)
      - Townships 2 South (Sylvan, Lima, Scio, Ann Arbor, and Superior Townships) (Folder 17)
      - Townships 3 South (Sharon, Freedom, Lodi, Pittsfield, and Ypsilanti Townships) (Folder 18)
      - Townships 4 South (Manchester, Bridgewater, Saline, York, and Augusta Townships) (Folder 19)
Related Records
Brown family. Papers, ca. 1873-1945. Includes a small amount of material relating to Arthur Brown.
Washtenaw County (Mich.). Records, 1827-1967. Includes correspondence of Arthur Brown as County Clerk and original mortgages for Washtenaw County. These are not the mortgage volumes indexed by the abstracts, but are the original folded paper mortgages.
The volumes of deeds, mortgages, and other legal papers abstracted and indexed in this collection are held by the Washtenaw County Clerk-Register's Office.